[engine starts]
[Jerry] This is a 1962 VW split-window
double-cab bus
in dove blue, primer gray, and rust.
The interior is gray vinyl and duct tape.
It's equipped with a 1971, 60-horsepower,
dual-port, four-cylinder engine.
What's cool about this bus, to me,
is that it was used as a service truck
for a VW Porsche repair shop
in Campbell, California.
It has a flatbed, two rows of seats
and an extra door on one side.
[phone ringing]
-[Jerry] Michael?
-[Michael] Jerry!
-[Jerry] Would you like to get a coffee?
-[Michael] Definitely! Come over.
-[Jerry] I'll be there in a few minutes.
-[Michael] Okay.
[Jerry] Hi, I'm Jerry Seinfeld, and this
is Comedians in Cars Getting Coffee.
Today, my guest is Michael Richards.
He played my next-door neighbor
for nine years on TV.
And we're still very close.
Why would you drink coffee?
What do you need, you need a boost?
-You looking for a boost?
-I need attention and I need a boost.
I want to get your reaction, unvarnished,
to this vehicle that I've chosen
specifically for you.
-Oh, gosh, that's...
-[laughs]
-I love it. I...
-What do you want?
-This is you, Michael.
-No, I like it. This is me.
I like this. I can throw my gear in it.
You don't have to have coffee.
It's just the name of the show.
-I don't think you drink coffee.
-I do.
What is it? Coffee, liquor, money?
-Is that your life now?
-[laughing] Yeah.
-Oh, Jerry!
-Coffee, liquor, money.
-Those are my priorities.
-Coffee, liquor, and a lot of money.
[Michael]
What else can I point out to you?
Now, this is the Getty Museum
over here on the left.
It was up for sale, Jerry.
They wanted $7.5 million.
Take a look at the front of it.
It's sliding down the hill.
They put that retaining wall
at the bottom
because they anticipate
more of it to come down.
-[Jerry] Oh, my God.
-And the swimming pool's already gone.
Half the pool's already slid down.
-[Jerry] Oh, my God.
-Now, look. Look!
-There's the swimming pool, Jerry. Look!
-[Jerry laughing]
Why would you buy 7.5...
And you know, inevitably,
it's all coming down.
Just a slight tilt in the axis,
and it's bubbly time.
You're under the sea.
[Jerry] Remember we played each other?
I played you and you played me
in that one episode
because we switched apartments?
The Kenny Rogers Roasters.
-God, I'm awful at this.
-The orange sign.
When you opened the door,
that orange light hit you
and you leaned backwards.
-That was one of the funniest bits.
-Oh, my...
But that was the intellectual aspect
of your comedy that I always appreciated.
That the light is so strong,
it's gonna bend my spine.
-Oh, God. Those were good days.
-Those were good days.
You gave me the role of my lifetime.
You gave me the experience of my lifetime.
Getting to play with you.
You know, being around you, Jerry,
I'm gonna turn into that crazy character.
It's gonna happen.
It's gonna gradually happen.
Go ahead.
[Michael] Can you turn
down one of these streets?
[Jerry] Yes, which?
-[Michael] El Medio?
-Yes.
[Michael] Up here
is where Sugar Ray Leonard lives.
He lives in this house right here.
-[Jerry] Which?
-Let's say hello.
-Are you friends with him?
-Yeah, I know him.
He may invite us in.
[Michael] Sugar!
Su-- Sugar!
[Jerry] Hey, Barry.
What are you doing here?
He told me Sugar Ray Leonard lives here.
This is Barry Katz.
The last time I saw him was
in my 2002 documentary, Comedian.
All he has to do is just...
-Are you on your way here?
-[Barry] Yes.
-[Jerry] Really?
-[Michael] Hey, hi.
Is Sugar in?
-[woman] Sugar in?
-[Michael] Sugar Ray Leonard live here?
[woman] No.
[Jerry] Oh, jeez.
Have you got the wrong house?
-[Michael] Whose house is it?
-[Barry] Jay Mohr.
-Who's Jay Mohr?
-He's a comedian and an actor.
It's the next house. I made a mistake.
-Are you sure?
-I'm sure of it. It's the next house.
So Jay Mohr lives
next to Sugar Ray Leonard?
We should say hello.
It'd be rude to not say hello.
-[Michael] Is that a real dog? Look.
-[Jerry] I didn't know he was gay.
-[dog barking]
-[Michael] I'm frightened.
I'm sure that was his house.
It's odd that...
Hmm...
-So, what do you think of it?
-Oh, I think the car's great.
It makes me want to take things
like this, you know, and just kind of...
You know... [grunts]
[speaking gibberish]
Can you imagine how upset
Jay Mohr is gonna be?
-Why? Really?
-If he finds out.
-[Michael] Did we excuse ourselves well?
-No.
-[Michael] Did we leave properly?
-It was rude.
We should go back.
No, I'm not going back.
We don't like to be rude but...
sitcom superstars
that have visited your home,
how long will you make them wait
out there on the sidewalk?
He may have been upstairs,
trying to get dressed.
As I said, they were working next door.
He probably didn't get much sleep.
Well, come down in a velveteen robe.
If he's got a dog that small,
-He could have a robe like that.
-He's got a robe, yeah.
[Michael] This is a long drive
for a cup of coffee.
Somebody waylaid me
at Sugar Ray Leonard's.
I'm sorry. I'm awful sorry.
-Now, tell me the truth--
-You know what's gonna happen?
-Do you really know Sugar Ray?
-Do I really know him?
-Tell me the truth.
-No.
I don't know him.
-See, I don't remember the past, too.
-Of course you don't remember the past.
There's nothing else to remember.
There goes 125 years of psychology
right out the window.
That kind of behavior, in the past,
-will wind you up in jail.
-Right.
Jail is such a... really a way
that a grownup would punish a child.
You go in there and you stay in there.
Robbing a 7-Eleven. Get in that cell!
I mean, to drive a car
through a crowd of people,
with a sandwich in your hand,
not even looking where you are going.
You sit in that cell
and think about what you've done.
Charles Manson,
that was supposed to be a party.
You should be ashamed of yourself.
And there'll be no dinner tonight.
[Jerry] How weird an experience
was that for Jay Mohr?
Who was at my front door?
What were they doing?
They were looking
for Sugar Ray Leonard's house.
-And they called my dog what?
-I don't want to say.
[Michael] Are we really going in there?
Are you serious? All these people?
We can't just walk in there going, "Hi."
We're not normal people.
You just walk right in and go, "I'm here"?
"I'm here, you deal with it."
[Michael]
That's why I bring my kit with me.
Now you don't know. See?
You don't know who I am, do you?
No. I know you're crazy.
I don't know, Jerry.
[Michael] Hey, look. There's me.
-[Jerry] That's the same hair.
-[Michael] That's the same guy.
-Isn't that amazing?
-[Jerry] That's amazing.
[Michael] That's amazing. How you doing?
[Jerry] I can't believe
it's the same exact hairstyle.
-[Michael] Look.
-[Jerry] Look at that.
-The same sunglasses. Wait a minute.
-You never know who you meet.
This is unbelievable, isn't it?
-Yes.
-I could probably hide out as you.
-And I could hide out as you.
-This is unbelievable.
Life is a hideout.
No one is gonna believe
that that just happened.
I think you should wear a hat
and some sunglasses or something.
Oh, Michael. Free yourself.
We're just raindrops
on a windshield, Michael.
[Michael] I wanna know
who's wiping me off.
[inaudible]
[Jerry laughing]
[Michael] Jesus. Who put that there?
I was thinking this morning,
I swear to God,
we would be rehearsing,
something dumb would happen, or weird
and you would just go,
"Well, that was interesting."
And the wheels would start to turn.
That's how you play chess. He makes a move
and you go, "Hmm, that's interesting.
[Jerry laughing]
Interesting."
I used to play chess. When I was
in the Army, I played. I was unbeatable.
I was very, very good at it.
With chess, there's ratings.
And chess master is about 2,100.
And I was playing a computer
on a 2,100 level.
-Really?
-Yeah.
So I had been playing that machine
for weeks,
and then I happened to be out
on Hollywood Boulevard
standing on the corner and I saw this man,
tattered, dirty.
He was a street person.
-And he had a chess set there to play.
-Right.
And I said, "You play chess?"
He says, "I do, I do."
-But it's a homeless guy.
-It's a homeless guy.
I said, "I'll tell you what,
I'll play you a game."
He goes,
"[mumbles] I'll play you two games.
I beat you two times,
you can't play me no more."
Puts out his hands, you know,
to see who's gonna go first.
Black, white. I pick. I'm white.
That means I have the first move.
I already have the advantage.
-Sitting on the sidewalk?
-I'm sitting on the sidewalk with him.
-I'm down here like this.
-Right.
So I move my piece out,
he moves his piece out very quickly.
Boom! I said, "Oh, he stops that move."
So I move a knight out,
he moves out the pawn.
He moves out the bishop...
In two minutes, he's moving--
He's got me in a defense...
Boom, checkmate! I'm like, "Whoa!"
He checkmated me in two minutes.
Nobody has ever checkmated me
in two minutes.
Nobody. Not even the machine
can checkmate me in two minutes.
But this time, I said,
"Okay, let's play. Let's play chess."
He makes me pick. I go first again.
Okay.
I lean in. He moves out his knight,
I move my bishop...
-Ba-ba-ba... Checkmate!
-[laughing]
Faster than the first time.
So, now he's putting his stuff away.
I'm going, "Come on. Let's play again."
He goes, "No, no, no. I beat you
two times, you can't play me no more."
I'm walking down...
Following the guy down the street...
going, "Let's play."
He goes, "No, no, you leave me alone.
I don't wanna play..."
I'm going, "Come on,
let's just play another game. Come on."
He wouldn't play me.
I went home, I called a friend
who's a professional chess player.
I called him up. I said, "Leon, I played
a guy on the street who beat me twice."
He goes, "Yeah, you played a savant.
When I'm in tournaments in a city, I look
for those guys, to play those guys."
I say, "You beat them?" He goes, "Never."
-Really?
-Really.
I always thought, "Can you get
one of those guys in a tournament?"
Imagine. He says, "You can't hold them
in place. They're crazy."
But they're unbeatable.
So he could really be
the greatest chess player in the world.
Possibly... Most likely.
He told me in the beginning.
"I beat you two times, that's it.
We don't play anymore.
You can't play me anymore."
Why would he set a rule like that?
Because he's done it over and over again
and he doesn't have a lot of time
to be fooling around
with somebody he can beat so easily.
That's probably why.
What was it that he was able to do
so well that he could win so fast?
He saw the moves before they took place.
This is where it gets a bit metaphysical.
Perhaps you have to be ultimately crazy.
-You think he was a clairvoyant savant?
-Or dislodged
from the kind of reality
that we're all adjusting to.
There are other kinds of realities,
other kinds of zones
-to inhabit.
-Right.
Great artists have inhabited zones
and then it becomes a new paradigm.
People go, "Wow, we hadn't thought
about going there."
I invented a chessboard.
I wanted to play it in the round.
So you're, like,
on the north and the south pole,
and your pieces...
So you can play in all directions.
That's when I had to stop playing chess.
-Bernie Brillstein.
-Showbiz legend, indeed.
-Right.
That was when I was doing Fridays.
He was executive producer.
He came in. He's a big man.
And not just physically,
but his presence. What everybody knew,
-He was like a lion.
-that when Bernie walked into a room,
-Right.
-somebody just walked in the room.
Says, "What do you think, Bernie?"
He goes, "It's gold."
[Jerry laughing]
Which then became Banya's line,
on the show.
-You remember that?
-Oh, my God, you gave him that line?
-"It's gold, Jerry?" Oh, man.
-Yeah.
You don't miss a beat.
You pick it all up.
Well, it's in the air. It's in the color.
I remember when we were putting
the show together,
first thing I said when they said,
"Well, how about Michael Richards?"
I went, "Is he available?
Is Michael Richards available?"
You had to audition
with two other guys for the network.
Two others?
You brought me back three times.
There was a room of different people
to read against.
But it was like chess.
I knew I was gonna get the part.
-You did?
-I knew it on the first time I met you.
-Really?
-I knew it. I never said a thing.
And I never said it to you.
I knew when I started reading with you.
I just said, "They can't pass that up."
You just feel the hand of the universe
going, "You two are gonna be together."
But I could've played Kramer
for the rest of my life.
Yes.
That character would fit
into any situation.
There was a great universality
to the soul of that character.
-I went to Bali. Get away.
-Right.
Get away for a little while.
Like to just step away from the world.
I go out into the jungle.
I'm way deep into the jungle now.
And I see some naked people,
and they point at me. They go...
"[speaking gibberish] Kramer!"
"This is Kramer."
They recognized me from the show.
They had a hut with a cable
out there somewhere. They could watch--
They had a little television.
They watched the show.
In the jungles of Bali.
You know those performers
who just love it?
-Yeah.
-It was always a struggle with me.
[groans]
No, no.
I don't accept the judging of process.
Doesn't matter that you rehearse
with your nose up against the flat,
saying lines.
-Doesn't matter.
-You used to see doing that?
Yes. We're all trying to get
to the same island.
Whether you swim, fly, surf,
or skydive in, it doesn't matter.
What matters
is when the red light comes on.
Okay. Because sometimes
I look back at the show
and I think I should have
enjoyed myself more.
Michael, I could say that myself.
But that was not our job.
Our job is not for us to enjoy.
Our job is to make sure they enjoy it.
-And that's what we did.
-Ah.
You know, that's beautiful.
That's beautiful.
Because I think I worked selfishly.
And not selflessly.
-It's not about me. It's about them.
-Yes. No.
Yes.
Now, that's a lesson I learned
seven years ago,
when I blew it in the comedy club.
Lost my temper
because somebody interrupted my act
and said some things that hurt me,
-and I lashed out in anger.
-Right. Right.
I should have been working
selflessly that evening.
Most of the time,
when I'm in that zone, I am selfless.
Right. You told me that you had done
a couple of sets.
-No, I never--
-Do you want to?
Sometimes, I say, "I must. I should."
And normally, I would have...
[mutters]
...gone in and played around
with this material.
But, no. No, I... [stammers]
I busted up after that event
seven years ago. It broke me down.
It was a selfish response.
I took it too personally.
And I should have just said,
"Yeah, you're absolutely right.
I'm not funny.
I'll go home and work on my material.
I'll see you tomorrow night."
[speaks gibberish]
And split. Or something. Anything.
But, you know,
it's just one of those nights.
And thanks for sticking by me.
-Really, you...
-There was no issue with that.
-Well, I mean, it meant a lot to me.
-That's nice.
But inside,
it still kicks me around a bit.
Okay, well, that's... You know...
That's up to you.
-Yeah, [stammers] that's a big...
-That's up to you
to say, "You know,
I've been carrying this bag long enough.
-Yeah.
-I'm gonna put it down."
Yeah. Yeah...
[inaudible]
[Jerry] Well, I hope that you do consider
using your instrument again...
[Michael] Thanks.
[Jerry] ...because it's the most
beautiful instrument I've seen.
-[Michael] Oh, Jerry. Thanks, buddy.
-It is. Yeah.